What's your stance on it? Do you ever
have patients having to donate blood?
>> You know, I do. Um, it's not many. It's
probably about, you know, 15 to 20% have
an issue where they have to donate over
time. Usually, we can get that down.
You know, in other words, even people
who
initially have to donate a lot, we over
time we reduce or eliminate the need for
that.
There's a huge controversy right now um
that spans one side of it is if if
you're hematocrit or the percentage of
your blood cells that are red blood
cells which testosterone increases if it
gets even a little bit high. Okay,
normally in men roughly about 40 to 50%
is nor is considered normal. Okay, it
changes from lab to lab. But there are
some doctors that think, okay, it's 51%,
that's really dangerous. We need to
immediately get this patient
flabbotomized. We need to remove one
unit of blood. Removing one unit of
blood, you know, they always taught us
in residency about drops here um
hematocrit about 3%.
Um and so that's what every patient
needs. The second it's even 50.1%.
They have to go immediately to the
hospital, not the Red Cross. They go
right to the outpatient infusion center
and we remove blood. Even if it's a
Sunday, we have to do it. Okay, that's
one side. The other side is
who cares? Don't even check. It doesn't
matter. It's not dangerous. Why do they
think it's not dangerous? Oh, well, look
at all these people that live above
5,000 ft. Okay, the Black Hills of South
Dakota. I think um Rapid City is like at
5,400 feet or something like that. A lot
of these patients, especially if they
live on a mountain in Rapid City, their
hematocrid at baseline is already high
above average. Okay, they don't die of
blood clots is what these proponents
say. And so probably it's fine. Okay,
because what used to be conf we used to
in medicine call anytime your red blood
cells got high something called
polyythemeia.
>> It turns out that that's not the correct
way to use the term polyythemeia really
means an increase in platelets usually
your white blood cell line and your
arythroidid lineages too. So your red
blood cells however the correct term for
when it's just your red blood cells is
arythroytosis. So there are certain
diseases um certain cancers of the of
the bone marrow called myop
proliferative neoplasms.
Um the most common one and you'll
understand once I say the name of this
this disease if you're an audience
remember why it gets confused is called
polyythemeia vera which is a condition
where yes your red blood cells are
increased and yes you have a very high
risk of developing blood clots. In fact,
last I read, 40% of people with
polyythemeia vera are not even diagnosed
until they have a blood clot. So they go
to the hospital, they get diagnosed with
blood clot, do some genetic testing,
whatever. Now, now we know you have
polyythemeia vera. Okay. So using those
terms interchangeably for many decades
has has just mistaught a lot of doctors
and thinking that red blood cells going
up is the same as this other condition
that is highly associated with blood
clots. And it's not true.
So, so yeah. So those are the two
extreme sides is one you have to treat
everybody like they have bone marrow
cancer and the second it gets even a
little high you have to either stop it
or phabbotomize them. The other side is
don't even check it. It doesn't matter.
It's not dangerous. Never been proven to
be dangerous. I'm in the middle of those
two. Okay. Uh I have a pretty high
target for phabbotomy. I think it should
be around 55%.
I think it should be there's a reason
why it's why I have a target of 55% that
I could explain it if you're interested.
Um, but that's what I use. So, that gets
me around 20% of people. And, uh, also
another big thing we do is we check iron
levels every 3 months. You know, we
don't let people donate if they're
already iron deficient.
um or we replete their iron at the same
time or what we have some strategy
because what does happen a lot is people
go to TRT clinics they're told hey you
got to go donate blood every two months
regardless of what your hematocrit is
and they end up becoming iron deficient
without anemia which is possible it's
possible to be iron deficient and not
have anemia um which a lot of guys don't
understand so some guys feel bad on TRT
not because of the TRT but because of
all the blood donation has depleted
their iron stores. That I wouldn't say
is super common, but it happens with
fairly high frequency.
>> Mhm. I know a lot of men that will see
this video later, they will ask why the
55%. Again, it's a number. Why 54 okay
and 55 not okay?
>> So, the reason why it's why my target
again this is a this is like an opinion
thing. is not um uh like I have so much
data and this 55 is so much better than
54. It comes from the hematology society
guidelines when I say society various
international society guidelines on when
you should phabbotomize someone with
chronic hypoxmic lung disease. So if you
have uh what people commonly refer to as
emphyma, let's say you were a lifetime
smoker, now you have emphyma or what
should be called COPD. A lot of times
you develop high red blood cells. Okay,
the concern anytime your red blood cells
get high or your hematocrit gets high is
that your blood clot risk is higher.
Okay, that's never really been proven in
anybody but those bone marrow cancer
patients I just told you about, which
they have reasons other than just a red
blood cell count for why they have an
increased clotting risk. They have
platelet issues. They have um tumors
that secrete various things that that
that promote blood clotting um that
people with just as arythroytosis don't
have. So what happens with these chronic
lung disease patients is they get
phbotomized but at a 55% or above
target. It's a high target because again
we want to balance the number one risk
of iron deficiency. Chances are their
stimulus for continuing to to get
ariththroytosis is still going to be
there. They're still going to keep
smoking in the same way that someone on
TRT the stimulus will still be there.
the way that smoking induced
ariththroytosis or lung disease induced
ariththroytosis
um those mechanisms and with TRT they're
not exactly the same but it's the T the
way that testosterone increases your red
blood cells is definitely not the same
as the way these bone marrow cancers
increase your red blood cells so I think
it's a good balance between
um just like careful caution And um
recognizing that we don't fully
understand the risks of high hematocrit
certainly hematocrit that is a standard
deviation above the normal range.
There's not a lot of studies there are
some studies in people um with high
altitude induced ariththroytosis
um that shows you know they don't have
an increased clotting risk but again
those the mechanisms are not the exact
same. So there it may be the case that
in the future we find out there is no
risk. It may be in the future we find
there is a risk. Um but I think after 80
years of treating people with
testosterone it's it's better to just
balance between in areas where you don't
fully have all the information
settle on something reasonable.
>> You know you don't need every patient to
go donate blood every 60 days. that is
incredibly
um overdoing it. At the same time, do
you just ignore it? You know, I don't
know that the medical legally it's
impossible to do because people will get
blood clots. Okay. Um and you know, if
they get a blood clot and they're on the
testosterone, the testosterone is going
to be blamed.
>> Yeah. Yeah,
>> even if they had a total knee
replacement a month prior,
>> you know, which is highly associated
with blood clotting risk.
>> Um, you know, that's just the way it
goes. So, it's a mixture where I arrived
at is a mixture of practical concerns
and balancing a lot of unknown risk and
to be perfectly honest since I'm known
for being very blunt, medical legal
concerns. because I don't want my
patients going to their primary care
doctor and then being like, "What the
hell is it? Your hematocrit's 62% and no
one's checked it in a year."
>> That makes you look really bad.
>> Um, and that's just the truth. That's
part of the consideration, too.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, that being said, do I have
physician patients that say to me,
"Yeah, I know my 57, and I know you're
going to tell me I need to donate, but f
you, I'm not." And that's fine if it's
their choice. That's completely fine
with me if they choose to do that.
>> Uh but that's where things stand and
that's kind of where I stand.